<!DOCTYPE html>
<html lang="en" prefix="og: http://ogp.me/ns#">
	<head>
		<meta charset="utf-8" />
		<meta name="viewport" content="width=device-width, initial-scale=1" />
		<title>BCHS//portability: source configuration</title>
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="https://fonts.googleapis.com/css?family=Alegreya+Sans:400,400italic,500,700" />
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="https://maxcdn.bootstrapcdn.com/font-awesome/4.7.0/css/font-awesome.min.css" />
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="highlight.css" />
		<link rel="stylesheet" href="portability.css" />
		<link rel="shortcut icon" type="image/png" href="/favicon-196x196.png" />
		<link rel="shortcut icon" sizes="196x196" href="/favicon-196x196.png" />
		<link rel="apple-touch-icon" href="/favicon-196x196.png" />
		<meta property="og:title" content="BCHS//openradtool: translation tools" />
		<meta property="og:image" content="https://learnbchs.org/logo-blue.png" />
		<meta property="og:url" content="https://learnbchs.org/translate.html" />
		<meta property="og:type" content="website" />
		<meta property="og:description" content="Manage translations for your openradtool configuration." />
		<meta name="description" content="Manage translations for your openradtool configuration." />
	</head>
	<body>
		<section itemscope="itemscope" itemtype="http://schema.org/WebPage">
			<nav id="mainnav">
				<div>
					<span>Porting series</span>:
					<span class="link"><a href="portability.html">intro</a></span>
					<span class="link"><a href="portability-page2.html">config</a></span>
					<span class="link"><a href="portability-page3.html">testing</a></span>
				</div>
			</nav>
			<header id="mainhead">
				<img itemprop="image" src="logo-blue.png" alt="BCHS Logo" />
				<h1>
					<a href="index.html" itemprop="name">BCHS</a>
				</h1>
				<nav>
					<a href="tools.html"><span>tools</span></a>
					<a href="easy.html"><span>example</span></a>
					<a href="https://github.com/kristapsdz/bchs"><i class="fa fa-github"></i></a>
				</nav>
			</header>
			<article id="article">
				<header>
					<p class="intro">
						Your software using the <a href="https://www.openbsd.org">OpenBSD</a> programming environment
						needs to be ported to other systems.
						What first step do you take?
					</p>
					<figure>
						<article data-sblg-article="1"></article>
						<figcaption>
							On second thought, maybe porting isn't a good idea&#8230;
							Run away!  Run away!
						</figcaption>
					</figure>
					<p>
						The above toy program accounts for Linux, NetBSD, FreeBSD, OpenBSD, Mac OS X, Solaris, and
						IllumOS.
						The macro soup is because <a href="https://man.openbsd.org/memmem.3">memmem(3)</a> is a GNU
						extension and <a href="https://man.openbsd.org/reallocarray.3">reallocarray(3)</a> (which here
						is superfluous, but used for exemplar's sake) is an OpenBSD extension.
						Both of these functions are pretty&#8230; normal, which makes the complexity particularly
						disenchanting.
					</p>
					<p>
						Obviously adding this for each file, each function, puts an impossible burden on developers.
						This is when a configuration script comes into play: it can feature-detect on the target system
						and output the correct macro soup into a shared header file.
						A compatibility source file, included when linking, can provide missing functions.
					</p>
					<p>
						The <a href="https://www.bsd.lv">BSD.lv</a> tools I wanted to port all used and use 
						<a href="https://github.com/kristapsdz/oconfigure">oconfigure</a> for this purpose.
						It received the lion's share of attention in this portability work.
					</p>
				</header>
			</article>
			<article>
				<section>
					<h2>history</h2>
					<p>
						The <a href="https://www.bsd.lv">BSD.lv</a> tools I wanted to port all usd
						<a href="https://github.com/kristapsdz/oconfigure">oconfigure</a> as a simple portability
						shim.
						This script was originally forked from <a href="https://mandoc.bsd.lv">mandoc</a> in 2014 for
						use in <a href="https://kristaps.bsd.lv/kcgi">kcgi</a>.
						Originally, it feature-tested for <a href="https://man.openbsd.org/memmem.3">memmem(3)</a> and
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/strtonum.3">strtonum(3)</a>, which weren't (aren't) available
						on Mac OS X, and provided compatible functions if these weren't detected.
						You can see its original import in commit
						<a href="https://github.com/kristapsdz/kcgi/commit/a5ff55cc8ea196619fbb364503906b0e6a6ec3e4#diff-e2d5a00791bce9a01f99bc6fd613a39d">a5ff55c</a>,
						with the original file called
						<a href="https://github.com/kristapsdz/kcgi/blob/a5ff55cc8ea196619fbb364503906b0e6a6ec3e4/configure">configure</a>.
					</p>
					<p>
						The script simply declared whether these functions existed or not as defined from a shell script
						compiled and run during configuration.
					</p>
					<figure>
						<article data-sblg-article="1"></article>
						<figcaption>
							Original test for <a href="https://man.openbsd.org/strtonum.3">strtonum(3)</a>.
							On OpenBSD, this would compile and run fine.
							On Mac OS X, the function would not be located.
						</figcaption>
					</figure>
					<p>
						The results were output into a header file <span class="file">config.h</span>, which was
						in turn included by the system sources.
						Below you can see an example.
						The <code>HAVE_xxx</code> defines were inserted based if the test passes.
						Compatibility functions were all in <span class="file">compat.c</span>, which also included 
						<span class="file">config.h</span>had <code>ifndef</code> guards around compatibility function.
					</p>
					<figure>
						<article data-sblg-article="1"></article>
						<figcaption>
							A <span class="file">config.h</span> generated by the earliest versions of the
							<code>configure</code> script in kcgi.
							In this case, both functions were detected.
						</figcaption>
					</figure>
					<p class="aside">
						(Can you spot the portability issue in the above?  If a system without 
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/memmem.3">memmem(3)</a> includes this, it's possible that
						<span class="file">sys/types.h</span> wouldn't be included, which defines
						<code>size_t</code>, resulting in a compilation error.)
					</p>
					<p>
						Sources would include the configuration header <span class="file">config.h</span> and link to
						the compatibility sources.  Let <span class="file">main.c</span> below be an example file.
					</p>
					<figure class="centre">
						<ifindingsmg src="portability-fig2.svg" />
					</figure>
					<p>
						By <strong>2016</strong>, there were about a dozen tests in the script (you can see it in
						<a href="https://github.com/kristapsdz/kcgi/blob/9ef04cbe1d1f62f199db14870dce5fd1071b1da4/configure">configure</a>
						for this date), with roughly half of them providing a compatibility function if not found.  I
						started to want this functionality for other systems, so I created a new repository called
						<a href="https://github.com/kristapsdz/oconfigure">oconfigure</a> to abstract the work.
					</p>
					<p>
						First I pulled in <a href="https://mandoc.bsd.lv">mandoc</a>'s new features for a site
						configuration script, which overrode test results, and to emit Makefile configuration variables
						as well.
						To keep things simple, I then had all tests and compatibility functions put into single files.
						This way, new projects needed only to copy
						<span class="file">configure</span>,
						<span class="file">compats.c</span>, and
						<span class="file">tests.c</span> to use the shim.
					</p>
					<figure class="centre">
						<img src="portability-fig3.svg" />
					</figure>
					<p>
						At the time and for some time after, the extra <span class="file">Makefile.configure</span> file
						didn't do much, but <span class="file">compats.c</span> and <span class="file">tests.c</span>,
						and the logic of <code>configure</code>, grew significantly.
					</p>
					<p>
						Prior to the porting effort, <code>configure</code> had a bit under three dozen feature tests,
						going so far as to provide the <a href="https://man.openbsd.org/queue.3">queue(3)</a> and 
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/tree.3">tree(3)</a> macro sets.
					</p>
				</section>
			</article>
			<article>
				<section>
					<h2>progress</h2>
					<p>
						One of the biggest problems with portability when I started this adventure was the location of
						dependencies.
						Most of the tools used <code>-lexpat</code>, <code>-lz</code>, and <code>-lsqlite3</code>.
						However, <code>-lsqlite3</code> sometimes needed <code>-lpthread</code>, sometimes not.
						More importantly, some portable functions existed on target platforms but required special libraries.
						For example, <a href="https://man.openbsd.org/md5.3">md5(3)</a> exists on FreeBSD, but requires
						<code>-lmd</code> for linking.
						Then on IllumOS, all socket functions required <code>-lsocket -lnsl</code>.
					</p>
					<p>
						To date, it was the job of the porter to know which libraries and library paths were required
						and pass them to the script.
						On these many new systems, <strong>I was the porter</strong>, so this got old real fast.
					</p>
					<figure>
						<article data-sblg-article="1"></article>
						<figcaption>
							Porting required knowing the correct paths for all systems.
							This invocation was required for statically compiling on OpenBSD.
							Obviously this put a huge burden on the porter!
						</figcaption>
					</figure>
					<p>
						The first big change was to allow for the portability layer to stand on its own and not require
						porter intervention.
						To wit, I taught <code>configure</code> to test and export whether platform-specific libraries
						were required for functions in the portability shim.
						For example, FreeBSD configuration set <code>LDADD_MD5</code> in the generated
						<span class="file">Makefile.configure</span> to the required library.
						Other systems left this empty.
						Thus, a <span class="file">Makefile</span> including this would no longer need a porter to pass
						the library during configuration&#8212;it added <code>$(LDADD_MD5)</code> where required.
					</p>
					<p>
						The second big change was to take advantage of a utility in OpenBSD's base <i>specifically
							designed</i> for the use case of locating libraries:
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/pkg-config.1">pkg-config(1)</a>.
						By using this, I no longer needed to supply the include and library paths for target systems: I
						would use <a href="https://man.openbsd.org/pkg-config.1">pkg-config(1)</a> to do it for me.
					</p>
					<figure>
						<article data-sblg-article="1"></article>
						<figcaption>
							I no longer needed to anticipate the library locations on all platforms.
							<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/pkg-config.1">pkg-config(1)</a> is supported on most
							systems, and on others may be tackled as-needed.
						</figcaption>
					</figure>
					<p>
						Once these basic steps were accomplished, I no longer needed to pass system-specific flags each
						time I moved to another system.
						I was able to focus on the nitty-gritty of providing compatibility functions, macros, and
						handling diverse header layouts.
					</p>
				</section>
			</article>
			<article>
				<section>
					<h2>nitty-gritty</h2>
					<p>
						After the <code>configure</code> script was smart enough to plumb its environment, next came
						handling discrepencies between systems.
						This section covers some of the major issues encountered, and isn't specific to the <q>new</q>
						systems involved in this porting effort.
					</p>
					<p class="important">
						<strong>This isn't a name and shame section</strong>.
						Working in a diverse environment is what it is.
						(On some systems, however, there can be&#8230; questionable design choices.)
					</p>
					<h3>strings</h3>
					<p>
						This was one of the first components managed by the script.
						I've read many arguments of why folks don't like
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/strlcpy.3">strlcpy(3)</a> and friends,
						but I also <strong>haven't read much code coming from those people</strong>.
						Anyway, I won't say anything more about this.
					</p>
					<p>
						It's fairly simple to test whether string functions exist: though some systems require macro
						soup to enable these functions during compilation.
						On <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/libc/">glibc</a> systems, for example, it's often
						necessary to include <code>_GNU_SOURCE</code>.
					</p>
					<h3>memory management</h3>
					<p>
						OpenBSD's better memory handling functions (e.g.,
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/reallocarray">reallocarray(3)</a>,
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/explicit_bzero">explicit_bzero(3)</a>, etc.)
						are slowly making their way into other systems.
						There seems to be less contention over these than the string functions.
					</p>
					<p>
						Unfortunately, including these extensions requires some macro soup.
						On Linux machines, either <code>_GNU_SOURCE</code> or <code>_DEFAULT_SOURCE</code> must be
						defined (for older and newer systems, respectively).
						However, if <code>_XOPEN_SOURCE</code> is also defined, such as for endian functions, then this
						macro conflicts with <code>_DEFAULT_SOURCE</code>.
						The solution is for both <code>_GNU_SOURCE</code> and <code>_DEFAULT_SOURCE</code> are required.
						What a pain&#8230;
					</p>
					<h3>randomness</h3>
					<p>
						As it currently stands, only OpenBSD supports high-quality non-blocking random numbers with the 
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/arc4random">arc4random(3)</a> family.
						Users of other systems must either depend on low-quality numbers or system-specific measures.
					</p>
					<h3>endianness</h3>
					<p>
						While the traditional <a href="https://man.openbsd.org/ntohs.3">ntohs(3)</a>
						are fairly standard, the new <a href="https://man.openbsd.org/le32toh.3">le32toh(3)</a>
						style is more readable and handles more cases.
						Unfortunately, this type of interface is <strong>very</strong> diverse and requires both macro
						soup and compatibility.
					</p>
					<p>
						Mac OS X (Darwin) has its set of byte-swapping functions in
						<span class="file">libkern/OSByteOrder.h</span>.
						SunOS (Solaris, IllumOS) has its own in <span class="file">sys/byteorder.h</span>.
						Neither are documented.
						FreeBSD has the correct functions in the wrong place.
						All of these need to be detected and the proper macros set up for sane names.
					</p>
					<p>
						What's more is that, while the byte-swapping functions themselves exist, actually testing for
						endianness is an entirely different problem.
						While OpenBSD provides <code>BYTE_ORDER</code> and a simple test for little or big endian, other
						systems have their own versions of <code>_BYTE_ORDER</code> and so on.
						Fortunately, most modern compilers emit a <code>__BYTE_ORDER__</code> macro that can be used as
						a relatively-safe fall-back without relying on obscure system headers.
					</p>
					<h3>devices</h3>
					<p>
						The familiar
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/minor.3">minor(3)</a> and related functions are all over the
						place on different systems.
						Fortunately, the functions themselves are named in the same way, so it's simply a matter of
						finding the correct header file.
					</p>
					<h3>file system</h3>
					<p>
						The POSIX *at functions (e.g.,
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/mknodat.2">mknodat(2)</a>) are still not broadly supported.
						I anticipate this will get better, though.
						(Only recently did OpenBSD gain most of these!)
						Though these functions are standardised, or becoming standardised, they do require some macro
						soup for systems (such as SunOS) that require specific features be defined for usage.
					</p>
					<p>
						Unfortunately, these functions can't be portably emulated since pairing 
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/fchdir">fchdir(2)</a> and the target function, e.g.
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/mknod">mknod(2)</a>, has a race between the two.
					</p>
					<h3>restricted operation</h3>
					<p>
						To any actual programmer, OpenBSD's restricted operation functions
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/pledge">pledge(2)</a> and
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/unveil">unveil(2)</a> are gifts from heaven.
						No other system's facilities even come close in terms of practical security.
					</p>
					<p>
						The user-level restriction features, such as
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/setresgid">setresgid(2)</a>, seem to be slowly migrating.
						On earlier Mac OS X machines, these were entirely broken, which required additional plumbing to
						detect since the functions were there.
						Recent versions do not have this issue, so it remains simply a matter of portability.
					</p>
					<h3>hashes</h3>
					<p>
						OpenBSD has the simple
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/md5.3">md5(3)</a> and
						<a href="https://man.openbsd.org/sha2.3">sha2(3)</a> header files for MD5 and SHA2 (e.g.,
						SHA256) hashing.
						This is incredibly useful because one can use these powerful functions without needing to pull
						in external libraries such as <a href="https://www.openssl.org">OpenSSL</a> or
						<a href="https://www.libress.org">LibreSSL</a>.
					</p>
					<p>
						FreeBSD has the MD5 header but splits the SHA2 header into SHA256, etc.
						NetBSD has a single header for both but different variable types and slightly different function
						naming.
						(FreeBSD also requires linking to another library for its hash functions.)
						SunOS, which also needs the hash function library, almost has everything, but is missing several
						key functions (e.g., SHA256File).
					</p>
					<p>
						There's no <q>right way</q> to do this&#8212;all using the same type, or different types, or
						different header files&#8212;but the disparity causes big headaches  for programmers.
						In the end, it became easier to simply test for all functions and provide compatibility
						straight-up instead of testing for each variant and providing macro-soup to work between them.
					</p>
					<h3>passwords</h3>
					<p>
						OpenBSD has <a href="https://man.openbsd.org/crypt_checkpass">crypt_checkpass(3)</a>, which
						makes password hash generation and checking super easy.
						The fallback is the traditional <a href="https://man.openbsd.org/crypt.3">crypt(3)</a>
						interface, which is a nightmare.
						Unfortunately, this function requires a tremendous amount of macro goop to properly use.
						Linux requires <code>_DEFAULT_SOURCE</code> (actually <code>_XOPEN_SOURCE</code> but defining
						both <code>_GNU_SOURCE</code> and <code>_XOPEN_SOURCE</code> pull this in, while defining both
						<code>_XOPEN_SOURCE</code> and <code>_GNU_SOURCE</code> on newer glibcs will cause warnings).
						Many systems require a further <code>-lcrypt</code>, which is easy to test for.
					</p>
					<p>
						Linux (glibc) further notes that this function may be deprecated and hand-waves a replacement.
						It does not have a manpage on some systems, but the function still exists.
					</p>
					<p>
						The supported hashes is where it gets interesting.
						OpenBSD, FreeBSD, and newer Linux support Blowfish.
						NetBSD and Solaris do not.  IllumOS does (undocumented).
						If this weren't confusing enough, NetBSD's function behaves differently than the others: if it
						does not find the requested hash algorithm, it returns a <q>magic string</q> instead of
						<code>NULL</code>.
						It's a mess.
						The most portable is simply to use DES encryption.
					</p>
				</section>
			</article>
			<article>
				<section>
					<h2>keeping it together&#8230;</h2>
					<p>
						Finding the necessary macro incantations proved immediately problematic.
						Especially on Linux: adding a feature test on an older glibc would break on newer ones.
						This seemed to go on forever and required each change to be tested manually on many systems.
					</p>
					<p>
						In the <a href="portability-page3.html">next section</a>, I introduce BSD.lv's continuous
						integration that helped with this.
					</p>
				</section>
			</article>
		</section>
		<footer>
			<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><i class="fa fa-creative-commons"></i></a> 
			<a rel="author" href="https://github.com/kristapsdz">kristapsdz</a>
		</footer>
	</body>
</html>
